{"tossups": [{"question": "After fighting the KKK, this state's William Woods Holden was the first governor to be removed through impeachment. The non-Italian Red Shirts began to disappear from this state after helping Charles B. Aycock, \"the Education governor,\" defeat Spencer B. Adams. In the only successful coup in US history, one Fusionist government in this state was overthrown by a white mob. That 1898 event occured in this state's city of (*) Wilmington. Bennett Place, the site of the last major surrender of the civil war, is located outside this state's city of Durham. A lost colony in this state was the site of the civil war Battle of Roanoke Island. For 10 points, name this state where Roy Cooper governs from Raleigh.", "answer": "North Carolina", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "An essay by this man compares \"pounding on this door\" with a \"total desperation to enter,\" only for it to reveal that \"we've been inside what we wanted all along\" to finding the humor in Kafka. One essay by this writer recounts his trip to the 1998 Adult Video News awards, while in another he describes a weeklong trip on the cruise ship Zenith. This author, who gave a commencement speech at Kenyon College titled (*) \"This is Water,\" discussed whether boiling animals for \"gustatory pleasure\" is moral in his essay \"Consider the Lobster.\" A novel by this man set in the \"Year of the Depend Adult Undergarment\" is titled for a film that is so entertaining that its viewers die. For 10 points, name this writer who created Hal Incandenza in Infinite Jest.", "answer": "David Foster Wallace", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "One of these compounds undergoes a 4 plus 2 cycloaddition with an azide in a reaction considered the \"cream of the crop\" of click chemistry. That reaction is named after Huisgen. These compounds are formed when alkyl dihalides undergo two E2 reactions using a strong base. The \"terminal\" types of these compounds are highly acidic. Palladium is deposited on calcium carbonate in (*) Lindlar's catalyst, which is used for the partial hydrogenation of these compounds. These compounds' characteristic functional group contains one sigma bond and two pi bonds. The simplest one of these compounds is acetylene. For 10 points, name these compounds characterized by a carbon-carbon triple bond.", "answer": "alkynes [accept internal or terminal alkynes; prompt on hydrocarbons; do not accept or prompt on \"alkanes\" or \"alkenes\"]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One painting by this artist is thought to represent Hercules rescuing Alcestis from the underworld and depicts a red figure holding a limp woman; that work is The Abduction. Many members of Les Nabis are present in a \"Homage\" to this artist by Maurice Denis. This artist depicted a man ripping the covers off of a reclining nude woman in his response to Edouard (*) Manet's work Olympia. This person used triangular shaped patterns with the trees and title nude figures in another of this artist's paintings; that work is The Large Bathers. This artist often portrayed fruits in his still-lifes. This artist would become well-known for his portraits of a certain landmark while staying in Provence. For 10 points, name this artist who often depicted Mont-Sainte Victoire.", "answer": "Paul C\u00e9zanne", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In one text in this religion, a man wonders if his 'buttocks turn into cartwheels\" after death, and says that he will \"ascend into the sky with his spirit as a horse.\" A man rebuffs another's argument by mentioning how walking makes him happy in a debate in this religion about the happiness of fish. This religion urges people to be like uncarved wood, or pu, when describing ziran. This religion's founder is shown having a (*) sweet expression in the allegory of the vinegar tasters. One scholar in this religion asked if he was a man dreaming he was a butterfly or a butterfly dreaming he was a man in the Zhuangzi. A concept central to this religion is \"action through inaction,\" or \"wu wei.\" For 10 points, name this Chinese religion founded by Lao Tzu.", "answer": "Daoism [or Taoism]", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "Charles de Monchy was saved by this ruler's general at the Battle of Bl\u00e9neau. This non-American ruler used ravelins as part of their third system of fortification. This person had an affair with the Duchess of La Valli\u00e8re, which he hid from his mother, Anne of Austria. In a rebellion nicknamed after the slingshots used to smash windows, this ruler's former general, the Prince of Cond\u00e9, was defeated by (*) Turenne. That rebellion is known as the Fronde. This ruler fought the Grand Alliance in the Nine Years' War. This king's chief minister was Cardinal Mazarin. This king signed the Edict of Fontainebleau, which revoked the 1598 Edict of Nantes. For 10 points, name this longest reigning French king who was known as the \"Sun King.\"", "answer": "Louis XIV [accept Louis the Great or Louis le Grand; prompt on Louis; prompt on Sun King] [the second line refers to Vauban]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A tribunal that is held in this location, composed of nine ancestral spirits, orders a character to take wine to his in-laws and beg his wife to come back home with him. One character who lives in this location cries after learning how newborn twins are taken to the Forest of Evil from this place. That character from this location changes his name to Isaac after being converted to (*) Christianity by Mr. Brown. A character who lives in this location resents his lazy flute playing father Unoka and gained prominence after winning a wrestling match against Amalinze the Cat. The protagonist of a novel set in this location is exiled after his gun exploded and killed Ezeudu's son during a funeral. For 10 points, name this village which serves as the home of Okonkwo in Chinua Achebe's Things Fall Apart.", "answer": "Umuofia [prompt on Africa or Nigeria or Igboland by asking \"can you be more specific?\"]", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "The Dupuit-Thiem equation assesses these structures under steady-state conditions. A slug test is performed to determine the characteristics of these structures. The equation Q = KA over dh/dl was developed to apply to these structures. The perched variety of these structures lies above another in the vadose zone. Over-access of these structures, which are measured by (*) Darcy's Law, can lead to saline intrusions. Percolation recharges these structures, which form artesian systems in areas under pressure. The largest one of these structures in the U.S. is the Ogallala one in the Great Plains. The water table lies at the top of these structures. For 10 points, name these underground layers of rock which store groundwater.", "answer": "aquifers [prompt on groundwater or water table]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This mountain range is the subject of Joaquin Miller's most famous poetry collection. The Maidu people inhabit this mountain range. In the foothills of this mountain range, floods threatened to overwhelm the Oroville Dam. This mountain range contains large basaltic columns at Devils Postpile. The Kaweah and Kern rivers drain much of the southern portion of this mountain range, while the American, (*) Stanislaus, and Tuolumne all drain the northern portion. Tulare County in this mountain range is home to General Sherman, the world's largest living tree. This mountain range's Mount Whitney lies in Sequoia National Park, while this mountain range also contains much of Yosemite National Park. For 10 points, name this mountain range which covers much of eastern California.", "answer": "Sierra Nevada [prompt on North American Cordillera]", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "In one work, this artist asked the listener to \"take me to the lakes where all the poets went to die.\" One album cover by this artist depicts a polaroid picture with the artist's initials and year of birth written underneath. One song by this artist begins \"Salt air, and the rust on your door\" before continuing that the namesake month \"slipped away into a moment in time.\" Another song by this artist has the lines \"Headlights pass the window pane / I think of you.\" This artist wrote the songs (*) \"I Wish You Would\" and \"Out of the Woods.\" This artist worked with Jack Antonoff to produce the albums 1989 and Folklore. One song by this artist begins with \"Nice to meet you, where you been? / I could show you incredible things\" before continuing \"I'll write your name\" next to the title concept. For 10 points, name this artist who sang \"Blank Space\" and \"Bad Blood.\"", "answer": "Taylor Swift", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "This country executed Jopie Fourie for his role in the Maritz Rebellion. In that rebellion, a roadblock set up to catch the Foster Gang led to the death of Koos de la Rey. The Fagan Commission was supported by much of this country's United Party, which included much of this country's National Party led by J.B.M. Hertzog. A leader of this country was the only signer of the Treaty of Versailles to sign the UN Charter. The (*) Defiance Campaign in this country protested against its system of pass laws. The Colony of Natal merged with three others to form this country, where the Sharpeville Massacre took place. Jan Smuts was a prime minister of this country, which was also led by F.W. de Klerk. For 10 points, name this country formed after the Second Boer War where apartheid developed.", "answer": "Union of South Africa", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Mark Strand says that \"I am not thinking of [this thing], but [this thing] is thinking of me\" in his poem \"2002.\" In a poem partially titled for this phenomenon, the speaker describes a boy who is invited to be \"the smallest page at court,\" as well as pictures of \"King George with Queen Mary\" and a \"stuffed loon\" shot by Arthur's father. In addition to that poem about this phenomenon in \"Nova Scotia\", another poem titled for this phenomenon describes how \"the Dews grew quivering\" after the speaker (*) passed the \"Fields of Gazing Grain.\" That poem describes how the speaker \"put away / My labor and my leisure too / For [this figure]'s Civility.\" A poet described how this figure \"knew no haste\" while driving a carriage that \"held but just Ourselves  --  And Immortality.\" For 10 points, name this figure that the speaker \"could not stop for\" in an Emily Dickinson poem.", "answer": "death [accept \"First Death in Nova Scotia\"; accept \"Because I could not stop for Death\"]", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "An imbalance between elastase and a compound beginning with this letter can cause emphysema, a type of lung disease. Lewy body dementia is caused by the buildup of one compound beginning with this letter; that compound is also used as a marker for Parkinson's. A structure named after this letter appears in the upper right of a Ramachandran plot. Tumors in cells denoted by this letter cause excess secretion of (*) glucagon and are suppressed by insulin. Starch contains glycolytic bonds named after this letter. A structure denoted by this letter turns every 3.6 amino acid residues and is stabilized by hydrogen bonds. For 10 points, name this letter that denotes a type of helix found in protein secondary structure contrasted with beta sheets.", "answer": "alpha [accept alpha-1-antitrypsin or alpha-synuclein or alpha helix or alpha cells; prompt on AAT]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Jun Nagao arranged an addition to this piece for the Trouv\u00e8re Quartet in 2003, which includes a part for saxophone. At the beginning of the fifth movement of this piece, flutes, bassoons and harps play a theme suggestive of a ticking clock. Colin Matthews was commissioned by the Hall\u00e9 Orchestra to add an addition to this piece partially named after \"the Renewer.\" The first movement of this piece begins with (*) col legno strings playing in 5/4 time. This piece's final movement ends with a \"fade out\" effect produced by a door being slowly shut on an offstage women's chorus. One movement of this piece was adapted into the hymn \"I Vow to Thee, My Country\", while another served as inspiration for John Williams' Star Wars soundtrack. For 10 points, name this suite by Gustav Holst that includes sections like Neptune, Jupiter, and Mars.", "answer": "The Planets, Op. 32", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Broteas, a person with this profession, was forced to self immolate after he refused to sculpt another goddess on a mountain after sculpting Cybele. One person with this profession, who was the center of a hero cult in Boeotia, may have been born after three gods urinated into a bull's hide. One man with this profession was blinded by Oenopion after attacking (*) Merope. A person with this profession was transformed into a stag and torn apart by dogs after witnessing a goddess bathing. One hero was killed by a scorpion for boasting about his prowess in this profession. Another person with this profession collaborated with Meleager to kill the Calydonian Boar. For 10 points, name this profession of people like Atalanta and Orion, whose patron goddess was Artemis.", "answer": "hunter [accept huntress or hunting]", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "This ruler ordered the construction of an obelisk left unfinished in an Aswan quarry, which would have been the largest in the country then. This ruler's daughter Neferure may have been married to this ruler's successor. This ruler, who was sometimes called Maatkare, added twin obelisks to Karnak as well as the Red Chapel. This ruler's architect Senenmut built the Djeser-Djeseru as a mortuary temple in (*) Deir el-Bahari. This ruler sent Nehsi on a large expedition to Puntland that transplanted trees. This wife of Thutmose II may have had her monuments defaced by Thutmose III, her co-regent. For 10 points, name this longest-reigning female pharaoh of Ancient Egypt.", "answer": "Hatshepsut", "subcategory": "Ancient History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A character in this play asks \"Who does the clearing up?\" before wondering if \"Maybe they just leave them there.\" A newspaper in this play reports the story of an 8 year old girl who killed her cat as well as an old man who is run over after crawling under a truck. Two characters in this play discuss a football match between the Villa and Tottenham and later argue over the phrase (*) \"Light the Kettle.\" A house in this play is theorized by those characters to belong to an unnamed man named Wilson, and they receive notes like \"Two braised steak and chips\" and \"Two sago puddings\" from the title device. This play ends with one character pulling a gun on someone who comes through the door, only to realize the person is his partner. For 10 points, name this play about the hitmen Gus and Ben, a work by Harold Pinter.", "answer": "The Dumb Waiter", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This person names an equation that describes the time evolution of a non-equilibrium particle distribution function. This person is the namesake of a quantity equal to e to the power of negative beta times energy, and the classical partition function equals the sum of those namesake \"factors.\" This person's H theorem can be derived from their namesake (*) transport equation. This man showed that entropy was proportional to the logarithm of the number of microstates, which is engraved on his tombstone. For a monatomic ideal gas, average kinetic energy equals three-halves times temperature times this man's namesake constant. For 10 points, name this scientist whose namesake constant is symbolized k-sub-b.", "answer": "Ludwig Boltzmann [accept Boltzmann transport equation or Boltzmann factor or Boltzmann H theorem or Boltzmann constant]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In one work, this person portrays characters named \"Donkey Teeth\" and \"Ozamataz Buckshank.\" In another work, this person plays a referee who flags Hingle McCringleberry for excessive celebration. In a movie directed by this person, a character mistakenly plays an N.W.A. song when trying to call the police. In that movie, the Beach Boys song Good Vibrations is played during the murder of (*) Kitty and Josh. The Wilson family drives to Santa Cruz on a vacation before meeting the Tethered in one movie by this man. Chris Washington escapes from the Armitage House in a movie by this man. For 10 points, name this director of Us and Get Out who made many comedy sketches with Keegan Michael-Key.", "answer": "Jordan Peele", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "One figure in this work argues that it is \"not in the nature of things that a bad man should injure a better than himself.\" In this work, a man refutes an argument by likening himself to a \"trainer of horses.\" That man in this work compares believing in divine agency but not gods to believing \"in flute-playing, and not in flute-players.\" This work concludes with a man claiming that (*) death is either a \"state of nothingness\" or a \"journey to another place,\" and that dying is nothing to fear. The speaker of this work describes how the Oracle at Delphi said there was no wiser man than him. The central figure of this work calls himself a \"gadfly.\" Meletus and Anytus charge this work's speaker with atheism and corruption of the youth. For 10 points, name this Platonic dialogue depticing the trial of Socrates.", "answer": "The Apology of Socrates [or Apologia Socratis]", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "category": "Philosophy"}], "bonuses": []}